Finding Aid for Northside Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Michigan) records, 1959-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Northside Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Michigan) records
1959-2007
Northside Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Michigan)
86805 Ba 2
Northside Presbyterian Church is in partnership with St. Aidan's Episcopal Church, but holds separate services. This record group includes materials of Northside Presbyterian Church only. Included are session minutes, newsletters, church bulletins, and topical files.
4.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited by the Northside Presbyterian Church (Donor No. 6447 ) in 1961. Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Northside Presbyterian Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan began first with chapel services held in the former Popkins School. The year was 1959 and very soon thereafter, the congregation moved to the Psi Chi Medical Fraternity house located on Fuller Road. In 1961, the members of the congregation petitioned the Detroit Presbytery for formal recognition as the Northside Presbyterian Church. Subsequently twelve ruling elders were elected with the Rev. William S. Baker confirmed as Stated Clerk. On March 4, 1962, Reverend Baker was officially called by the congregation as minister to the church. He was formally installed by the Presbytery of Detroit on September 30, 1962.
On January 9, 1966, Northside dedicated a church center and education house located at 1679 Broadway and moved its activities from the Psi Chi Medical Fraternity to the new building. This began the church's partnership with St. Aidan's Episcopal Church, whereby the two congregations shared the same facility but held separate services.
In 1979, Rev. William Baker stepped down as minister of the church. Rev. Peter Boeve was appointed to the position of interim minister on December 16, 1979. He was appointed minister soon thereafter and served until March 1995.
The Northside Presbyterian Church Records document the church's activities since 1959. The record group is an ongoing one with the addition of materials (especially newsletters) on a regular basis. The records included consist of session minutes, newsletters, church bulletins, mailings to members, and subject files.
The record group has been divided into three series: Administrative Records, Publication,s and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.MichiganAnn Arbor.; Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.MichiganAnn Arbor.; St. Aidan's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
- Administrative records
  The Administrative Records series is comprised of eight subseries: Annual Reports and Minutes, Clerk, Leadership, Membership, Nurture, Stewardship, Worship, and Miscellaneous.
  - Annual Reports and Minutes, 1959-1986
    The first subseries, Annual Reports and Minutes, includes the meeting minutes and committee reports of the church's annual meetings as well as annual statistical reports to the general assembly. These span the years from 1959 to 1986.
    - Annual Congregational Meeting Minutes, 1969-1986 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1961-1969 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1962-1986 (Box 1)
    - Statistical Reports to the General Assembly, 1959-1980 (Box 1)
  - Clerk, 1961-1986
    The second subseries documents the responsibilities of the church Clerk. These files are comprised of correspondence, deacon's meetings and session minutes, as well as other related materials. Clerk materials date from 1961 to 1986.
    - Correspondence, 1962-1986 (Box 1)
    - Deacon's Meeting Minutes, 1971-1977 (Box 1)
    - Investment and Title Correspondence and Related Materials, 1970-1981 (Box 1)
    - Presbytery and Synod Correspondence, 1963-1981 (Box 1)
    - Session Minutes, 1959-1986 (Box 1)
      - 1959-1971, 1 volumes (Box 1)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970-1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976-1979 (Box 1)
      - 1980-1986 (Box 1)
    - Session Organization, Rules and Related Materials, 1970-1981; undated (Box 1)
  - Leadership, 1961-1982
    The third subseries, Leadership, is comprised of mission design statements, pastor's letters to the congregation, planning reports, and materials relating to pastoral relations. These date from 1961 to 1982.
    - Deacons' minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
    - Mission Design Statements and Corporate Concern, 1961-1978; undated (Box 1)
    - Pastor's Letters to the Congregation, 1960-1986 (Box 1)
    - Pastor's reports to session, 1962-1979 (Box 1)
    - Pastoral Relations, 1961-1979 (Box 1)
    - Planning Reports, 1971-1982 (Box 1)
  - Membership, 1963-1982
    Church membership materials date from 1963 to 1982 and include flyers and brochures, letters, mailing lists, committee reports and minutes.
    - Flyers and Brochures, 1963; undated (Box 1)
    - Inactive Members, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Letters to Students, 1968-1981; undated (Box 1)
    - Mailing Lists, 1965-1981 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Reports and Committee Minutes, 1963-1982; undated (Box 1)
  - Nurture, 1963-1986
    The Nurture series include general materials and letters from out-of-town and former members. Materials date from 1963 to 1986.
    - General Materials, 1963-1986; undated (Box 1)
    - Letters from Out-of-Town Members and Former Members, 1966-1981 (Box 1)
  - Stewardship, 1961-1986
    Church financial materials dating from 1961 to 1986 are contained in the Stewardship subseries. These include budgets, correspondence, financial reports and materials relating to the church's building fund.
    - Budgets, 1961-1983 (Box 2)
    - Building Fund Campaign, 1962-1966; undated (Box 2)
    - Debt Repayment Correspondence, 1961-1973 (Box 2)
    - Financial Secretary Reports and Treasurer Reports, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
    - Financial Secretary Reports and Treasurer Reports, 1976-1979 (Box 2)
    - Financial Secretary Reports, 1980-1986 (Box 2)
    - Financial records, 1959-1981; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - General Mission Pledges, 1963-1982 (Box 2)
    - National Missions Aid, 1963-1969 (Box 2)
    - Special Funds and Offerings, 1962-1982 (Box 2)
  - Worship, 1961-1981
    Worship materials date from 1961 to 1986 and include survey materials and service programs.
    - Questionnaires and Surveys, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Service Programs, 1961-1981 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - History and related background material, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Northside Chapel miscellanea, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
    - Rehill Gallery file (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Publications
  The second series, Publications, is comprised of weekly church bulletins and informational newsletters sent out to members.
  - Church bulletins, 1959-1986
    - 1959-1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968-1986 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1960-2007 (Box 4)
- Topical files
  The Topical Files series, dating primarily in the 1990s, includes much documentation of the various church committees, as well as minutes of congregational and session meetings.
  - Associated Ministries
    - 1996 (Box 5)
    - By-Laws and Articles, 1970; 1995 (Box 5)
    - Long Range Planning, 1989-1993 (Box 5)
  - Budgets, 1995-1997 (Box 5)
  - By-Laws, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Congregational Meeting Minutes, 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - Consultation, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1997 (Box 5)
  - Exegetical Notes, Peter Bower, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Financial Secretary Monthly Reports, 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - Homosexuality and the Church, 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - Leadership Committee, 1994-1996 (Box 5)
  - Local Evangelism Project, 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Map, Presbyterian Churches in Detroit Area (Box 5)
  - Membership/Nurture Committee, 1991-1996; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - More Light Committee, 1994-1996 (Box 5)
  - Nominating Committee, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Personnel Committee, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Redevelopment, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Session Agendas and Minutes, 1993-1996; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Small Church Study (Box 5)
  - Stewardship Committee, 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - Treasurer Reports, 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - Worship Committee, 1993-1996 (Box 5)